I am welcome to today's video.
In this video, I thought I would talk about why
we don't use a notepad for coding our material.
So here we've got a notepad running and behind it
I've got an ide by the way, just for your record,
an IDE stands for an integrated development
environment, We often call them IDs, or
sometimes we might even refer to them as editors.
Now, in terms of our editors, these
are the ones that I tend to use.
So if I'm doing things in C Sharp,
then I use Visual Studio, Uh, in
Java, I would use Intelligent J.
Idea With Python, I would use Pie charm in html.
I probably would go back to either using
Intelligent J Idea or I could use something
like Notepad Plus Plus, which is another
piece of software that I would use.
An older bit of software I used to
use was one called brackets.io, and
all of those would work really well.
So there are different types of IDE
for different types of programs.
For example, with Java, I know that you
can either do it in Intel J Idea, you can
do it in Net Beans, you can use Visual
Studio Code can also use, uh, Eclipse.
So there are all kinds of different IDE's
available ideally, you wanna stick with
just one and one that you become familiar
with and for me, Intel J was the one that
I've actually become quite familiar with.
Let me just remove all of that information a
moment and what I will do is give you a quick
demonstration of why we don't use Notepad.
So let's just start by writing a program so
I'm just gonna do a simple print line exercise.
So we'll just do system dot out,
dot print line, open bracket.
Hello world, okay and I'm also going to,
uh, take in a scanner so let's just use
a scanner so scanner, and I'm gonna call
it reader like I normally would do equals
new scanner, open bracket system.in.
As well as that, I need to
set up something to input.
So let's quickly do a system dot out, dot
print line open bracket, enter your name uh,
actually I don't wanna use print line I think
I'll just use print so let's set up a string,
string and I'm gonna call it name, equals and
it's gonna be reader read line and hopefully
that'll just read the line and that's it.
Okay.
So what I would then do is I would
take this program and I would run
it through something called Java C.
Java C is uh, a compiler, or rather it will
help compile my code into bytecode and Java
bytecode code is what we run using Java.
Before it would actually compile, it would
check it for errors and if there are any
errors it will pick them and report them
back to me and I know that what I've just
written for you, there's loads of errors.
You wouldn't notice it just to look
at it in the first instance cause
I'm getting no feedback at all.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
highlight all of this, copy it, minimize
it and now I'm gonna go into intelliJ.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna
create a new project that's called
Using an IDE and just run that.
I'm just going to run a new class, and
I'm just gonna call this, first program.
So there you go we've got our first program.
Okay.
Let's pop in our code and see how bad it is.
Okay, so there's a lot of stuff going on there.
First of all, I don't have a main method,
so none of this would actually run,
so let's just get that main method in.
So what I can do is highlight all
of this and paste it into here.
Formatting seems to have gone a bit awry
ah, that would be because I didn't put
a semicolon at the end of that line.
So let's do that.
It's complaining because it doesn't know what a
scanner is, so let's just sort that out before
it has a fit, so let's do that create local
no, I don't wanna do that, I want to use the
scanner so it can't resolve it at the moment.
Hmm wonder why?
Oh, I've got another problem up here,
let's put in a speech mark okay now
it seems to know what scanner is.
So let's solve this problem.
I'll enter and you'll see now I've got scanner
up here oh, sync so let's just do that.
Okay, so now we've got, Oh, why is that system,
Oh, it's because it's capital S for system.
So let's do that so as you can see,
this is what's called bug fixing.
So what I'm doing is I am debugging
the system by simply going through it
and identifying errors before I run it.
Cause if I try to run it in its current state,
I'm gonna get all kinds of errors coming up there
you go unclose string literal, that's here and
also I haven't got the semicolon at the end here.
This is not in the right place.
That should be a capital S.
You can see it's red, so it's kind
of telling you it's not right.
This needs to be a capital S also and what's
wrong with this over here or what I, what I
should be able to do, and this is something
you can do in an ide, is if I do reader dot,
it actually prompts me what I could type in
so as you can see, it should be next and then
capital L for line followed with the brackets.
That seems to work fine.
I've managed to be able to write
my program now better using an ide.
What else can I do with an ide?
Well, for a start I can actually run it.
So let's just run it and there you go it seems
to be working, so let's just type in a name, yep.
So that's working well.
Okay I'm happy with that.
And let's just output the name.
So let's just do something like, your name is,
and I'll put in name, now did you notice as soon
as I typed in the word name, let's just do that
again, plus look at the word name up here by
hover over over it says Variable is never used.
So that's something really useful to
know because that way then I know that
the variables that I'm using at the
moment aren't being used in the system.
So I'll create name and you'll see that
it lights up so that's really good.
There is something else that
you can actually do as well.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna create an equation.
So we're gonna use a couple of integers so I'm
gonna do num one equals one, and I'm gonna create
another iger called num two, and that equals 2.2
now you'll see that the whole thing's
got this crazy line going under it,
and if I hover over it, it'll actually
say, require type int provided double.
That's no good um, I need to either use
this as a double or use it as an integer.
In fact, the point is I wanted to make
it an integer, so I made a mistake there.
So it should be two, but as you can see
as i was typing it in, it identified
the error and flagged it up to me.
So what about a total, so let's create a total,
so actually I'm gonna create it like this, I'm
not gonna declare it, I'm just gonna write it and
look it's already identified a little error there.
So let's just do num one plus num two okay.
Now it's kind of highlighted that this is
a problem so cannot resolve simple total,
what that basically means, it isn't working
right now there are a couple of suggestions
on the bottom "Alt shift and enter" will
create a local variable called total.
So let's just try.
alt shift and enter and immediately it's,
it's suggesting I either create it as an
int, a long, a float or a double, so I
wouldn't be able to do that using Notepad.
Also, let's output the total.
So I'm gonna do, so ut that's a shorthand way
of writing the system.help, dot print line.
So I can actually do that I can actually
create some shortcuts that I can use.
So I'm just gonna say, The total is, and
then just simply do plus total like, so.
Now what I can do is I can put little dot here..
Now what that little dot is, it's a break
point, and what will happen is, if I run
this application in debug mode it will get
to that break point and stop the program.
So I'm gonna show you that happening.
So, up here we've got these run buttons.
Let me just run the application
just to show you it running.
Okay.
So I typed in the name Fred Press Return.
It'll say Your name is Fred and the
total is three so this is working fine.
Let's debug it, so when I run the
debugger, hit that, I'll type in the
name Fred again, just like I did before.
But this time what happens is it gets to
the break point and stops, and what it does
is it shows me down here, all the values of
everything that's going on, so it's showing me
what the reader is so I can view the reader.
I can look at the name, the
name currently equals Fred.
I can also see that num1
equals one, num2 equals two.
So I'm able to see what's going on
before it runs this application.
And can you see up here, it's
actually showing me number two.
Two, number one, one.
So it's actually putting the values in
and I can use this little dropdown to
see what we're doing with those values.
So that seems to be working really well.
Now over here we have some more tools.
So I've got step over, step into, force
step into, step out and run to cursor.
So I could put the cursor, um, down to
here and say, run to cursor and what
will happen is it'll run to that cursor.
Now you'll notice that total has a value
because we've actually run past that,
and you'll see here that num1 equals one.
num2 equals two total equals three
up here, by the way, you can actually
also see that name equals Fred.
So I'm able to see exactly what my variables
are doing whilst the program is running.
So this is kind of like freezing time,
this is like stopping time for a moment
so I can actually see what's going.
Now if I was to, uh, step over, this will just
carry on running and then it will stop so I can
step over again and you can see it's now finished.
We've now disconnected from the target
vm and it's showing me what the address
and what the transport socket is.
Okay, so you can see that the
whole program did its thing.
The total is three, which
is what it should appear.
So I can take out this break point and
all I have to do is click in that area.
So anytime you are using a piece of software with
an IDE and break points, you'll probably find
the break points are located along this area.
Okay, it's normally next to the line
number, so that's the reason why I would
use an IDE over notepad, and I hope you
can see the benefits of using an IDE.